Fatih SAYIN

Austin, TX 78729 | (512) 765 3221 | fmsayin@hotmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

Strategic, multidisciplinary Data Analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Combining my expertise and research analyst background in such areas to deliver the best creative data visualizations and actionable insights with perfect approximation algorithms. Proactively perfects skill sets and deepens experience with the tools VBA,

Python, Ipython, Pandas, SOL, MongoDB, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Tableau, Scikit-Learn and Spark.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization | 2019 Ivane Javakhishvili State University | Georgia | Ph.D. | 2009

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Data and Quantitative Analysis
- Decision Analytics
- Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling
- Data-Driven Personalization
- Big Data Oueries and Interpretation
- Data Mining and Visualization Tools
- Tableau

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions, Social Media Mining
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB
- Research, Reports, and Forecasts
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet.j

MOST RECENT PROJECTS

- 1. Project
- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

- 2. Project
- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (EuroLeague)
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs GDP data set was analyzed. The success of teams has positive correlation with the GDP of its country. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/ETL-Project-EuroLeague

MOST RECENT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

1. Heroes of Pymoli Game Data Analysis

• **Description:** Programmed a general python script to analyze the data for a game. Generated a report that breaks down the game's purchasing data into meaningful insights.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes_of_Pymoli

2. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude

• Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib

• **Description:** Coded a weather API python general script for over randomly selected 500 + cities across the world of varying distance from the equator to detect their temperature, humidity, cloudiness, and wind speed based on their latitude.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather_Py

3. Rental Movie Database

• **Description:** Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql challange

4. New York City Bike Analytics with Tableau

• **Description:** Analyzed New York City Bike Data which is the largest bike sharing program in the US. Aggregated the data to build a data dashboard, story and report with Tableau. Created geo maps, bar-pie-line charts with the aggregated columns in order to determine the insight of the data.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/New-York-City-Bike-Analytics-with-Tableau

5. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects

• **Description:** Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel

6. Web-Visualization

• **Description:** This is an analysis and visualization of weather of 500+ cities across the world. The main objective was to showcase the relationship of various factors like temperature, humidity, cloudiness and wind speed with respect to the distance from the equator.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io

7. Belly-Button Biodiversity: Bacteria Dashboard

• **Description:** Used Flask to design an API for the dataset and to serve the HTML and JavaScript required for the dashboard page. SQLite database file and inside of the Flask application code was used for the database as JSON file format, and uploaded Herokuapp.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Belly Button Biodiversity-Plotly-

	PROFESSIONAL AND ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE
Jan 2019 – Present	Data Analyst, Cosmos Trading Inc. Austin, Texas, USA
Oct 2018 – Apr 2019	Data Analytics and Visualization Boot Camp, The University of Texas at Austin
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Freelance Research Analyst, Austin, Texas, USA
Sep 2014 – Jul 2016	Founding Director of Research Center / Research Analyst, Canik Basari University,
_	Samsun, Turkey
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Assistant Professor, Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Jun 2009 – Jul 2011	Assistant Professor, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia